Guide to the Miss Indian America archive M0810
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Miss Indian America archive
1945-1984
1950s
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Brayer, Herbert Oliver
M0810
2.5 Linear Feet (5 boxes: 3 archival boxes and 2 flat boxes)
The Miss Indian America archive contains materials pertaining to the Miss Indian America pageant held during All American Indian Days in Sheridan, Wyoming from 1954 to 1984. This pageant was envisioned as an alternative to the Miss America pageant. Contestants in both pageants were young, unmarried women who represented their land of orign. Miss America contestants represented their home states and Miss Indian America contestants represented their tribe. The pageants were very similar and contestants in both demonstrated their talents onstage. Miss Indian America contestants did not wear swimsuits but instead wore traditional tribal dresses. The winner of the Miss Indian America pageant embarked on a speaking tour in order to gain awareness for a charity of her choice and also met with the winner of the Miss America pageant. The Miss Indian America pageant was one of the main events of the American Indian Days which celebrated tribal traditions and events over the course of three days.
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased by Stanford University, Special Collections in 1995.
Scope and Contents
The Miss Indian America archive consists of five boxes of materials. Included are photographs of both the Miss Indian America pageant and the All American Indian Days events which took place in Sheridan, Wyoming. The contestants' applications and multiple judges' notes are also included in the collection. Herbert O. Brayer, the creator of this collection was heavily involved in the pageant's organization, and the collection includes his writings, correspondence and newspaper clippings about his research on the Old West. Also included are tourism brochures, event schedules and programs of the All American Indian Days. Of note is a record of Indian tribal songs, prints by Randy Steffan and informational brochures designed for Native American children.
Along with materials about the Miss Indian America pageant are clippings, programs and photographs from the Miss America pageant from 1954- 1956.
Access to Collection
In the 1950s Sheridan, Wyoming resembled Jim Crow-era South with tensions between the Native American population and the white residents. In 1952, a young Crow Indian girl named Lucy Yellow Mule was selected as the Sheridan-WYO- Rodeo Queen leading to a movement to improve the relationships among the community members of Sheridan. Sheridan also won two awards the "Silver Anvil" National Honor Award and the George Washington Honor Medal Freedom Foundaton of Valley Forge Pennsylvania for promoting better understanding and tolerance between races. From these two awards, All American Indian Days was established. The event was intended to preserve Indian rituals, tribal games, clothing, art, language and stories.
The Miss Indian America Pageant began in 1954 as part of the All American Indian Days and was held each year in Sheridan, Wyoming. In 1984, the pageant moved to Bismarck, North Dakota where it was held until the mid- 1990s. The pageant was intended to select someone who would be a good public relations representative for the Native American community. Miss Indian America must be someone "dedicated to the cultural well-being of tribe, she must have a comprehensive knowledge of her people and be dedicated to their advancement. She must have the appearance, personality and poise to represent her people in the white community." The winner of the pageant spent a year traveling around the United States speaking about her tribe and Native American issues.
The contestants were unmarried women between the ages of 16 and 25. They were asked to wear traditional costumes including headdresses and feathers even if these accessories were not part of contestant's tribal outfit and present a talent. Each contestant also gave a personal gift to her sponsor. Most of the judges were white throughout the pageant's history.
Seavey, C. (2012, October 29). All- American Days are Gone. Casper Star Tribune. Retrieved from http://trib.com/news/local/casper/answergirl/all-american-indian-days.
Zhorow, I. (2013, July 12). Years Later, Miss Indian America Pageant Winners Reunite. WRUR.org. Retrieved from http://wrur.org/post/years-later-miss-indian-america-pageant-winners-reunite.
Kozol, W. (2005). Miss Indian America: Regulatory Gazes and the Politics of Affiliation. Feminist Studies, 31. Retrieved from http://www.jstor.org/stable/20459007.
Shoshone; Miss America Pageant, Atlantic City, N.J. -- History.; Native Americans of North America; Yurok Indians -- Music.; Cheyenne Indians; Hupa Indians; Wyoming; Gros Ventre Indians (Montana); Piegan Indians; Confederated Tribes of the Warm Springs Reservation of Oregon; Nez Perce Indians -- History; Blackfeet Tribe of the Blackfeet Indian Reservation of Montana; Confederated Tribes of the Umatilla Reservation, Oregon; Pawnee Indians; Crow Indians; Women.; Ute Indians; Navajo Indians -- Photographs.; Pueblo Indians -- Photographs.; Cayuse Indians; Kiowa Indians; Brayer, Herbert Oliver
- Correspondence of Dr. Herbert O. Brayer, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Letters to and from Dr. Herbert O. Brayer and his involvement in the Miss Indian America pageant. He is listed as being an author, editor, publisher and judge at All-American Indian Days.
- Pamphlets, photographs and brochures, 1955- 1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Included in this folder: Malki museum brochure February 1965; The Record August 1955; September 1956 newspaper clipping; Miss Indian America pageant working schedule September 1954 and a “Shining Water Woman” postcard
- Dr. Herbert O. Brayer's Notes and Writings, 1956- 1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Information about Rita Ann McLaughlin, a dental technician from the Hunkpapa Sioux tribe who won the pageant in 1955 is in this folder. Brayer’s writings is comprised mostly of information about All-American Indian Days which describes the event and lists the following tribes as being involved: Blackfeet, Gros Ventre, Piegan, Yurok, Pawnee, Hupa, Nez Perce, Unmatilla, Cayuse, Warm Springs, Kiowa, Shoshone, Ute, Pueblo and Navajo.
- Photographs, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Photographs of women in pageant at All- American Indian Days. Some of the photos are dated August 8, 1954. Also included is a one page article on Sandra Maey Gover, who was Miss Indian America IV in 1956.
- Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Included in this folder are the following photographs of women and events. Some additional photographs are unlabeled.
  Vivian Old Horn- Crow; Rosalene Bull over the Hill- Crow; Myrna Mae Williams; Crow and Cheyenne girl dancers; Mary Gueva Whiteman- Crow; Jemez Eagle Dancer; Old Bull Cheyenne; Kettle dance; Caroline Rosemary Motanic- Umatilla (2 photos); Sandra Mae Gover (Miss Indian America IV)- Pawnee; Lucy Yellowmule “Dwells where the Corn Grows”- Corn tribe.
- Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Photographs of Miss Indian America Ceremony. Not all photographs are labeled. Most of the photographs are of tribal members standing on a stage and potentially crowning that year’s Miss Indian America. Includes the following photograph: Theodore Lost Star- Blackfeet Chief and Peter Red Horn Jr.
- Photographs, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  This folder includes the following photographs:
  A wedding photo from April 10, 1955 of Mr. and Mrs. Ernest Charles James. She is the former Miss Arlene Wesley and Miss Indian America of 1953. Also in the photograph is Rev. Malcolm Norment, a pastor at the Yakima Indian Christian Church in White Swan. Also included are the following photographs: A photo of Sandra Mae Gover. A photo of Glenn Emmons, Commissioner of the Bureau of Indian Affairs. A photo of Mauice Petterson, director of the Koran Oriental band, Delores Jean McLaughlin, Queen of the Oriental band, Howar Leik, mayor of Casper and Harry Evans, Captain of the Guard at the Korean Temple. A photo of Miss Indian America runner up 1954-1955 including Wynema Rose Archambault, a Pawnee-Sioux tribes member from Pawnee, Oklahoma.
- Photographs, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Some of the photographs are dated August 8, 1954 Includes the following photographs: A photo with the following women from left to right: Arlene Wesley, 1953 Miss Indian America, Yakima Tribe, dancer and singer; Etta Leona Connor, Umatilla tribe, Pendelton, Oregon; Mary A. Turley, Cherokee, Tulsa, Oklahoma; Mary Louise Defender, Miss Indian America II 1954- 1955, Sioux; Miss Kay Price, Navajo, Sheep Springs, New Mexico; Tommie Bachand, Chippewa, Milwaukee, Wisconsin; Clara Joy, Old Crow, Lodge Grass, Montana. A photo of Judge Zahn “Flying Cloud” No. Sioux. A photo of Daniel Old Bull from Cheyenne. A signed photo of Woody Mercer made out to Herb. A photo of Miss Indian America III greeting Miss Indian America II. Arlene Wesley, 1953 Miss Indian America, Yakima Tribe, dancer and singer; Etta Leona Connor, Umatilla tribe, Pendleton, Oregon; Mary A. Turley, Cherokee, Tulsa, Oklahoma; Mary Louise Defender, Miss Indian America II 1954- 1955, Sioux; Miss Kay Price, Navajo, Sheep Springs, New Mexico; Tommie Bachand, Chippewa, Milwaukee, Wisconsin; Clara Joy, Old Crow, Lodge Grass, Montana. A photo of the following women: Arlene Wesley, Queen 1953, Mary Turley, Mary Lewis Defender, Queen 1954- 1955, Kay Price, Wynema Rose Archambault.
- Correspondence and photographs, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Photographs include Arapalo dancers, Judge H.B. Johnson and Sandra Mae Gover of the Pawnee tribe reciting the Lord’s Prayer in Sign Language with Clara White Hip of the Crow tribe singing and a group of portraits of contestants including Rose May Spencer which were mailed to Dr. Brayer at his address in Evanston, Illinois.
  This folder includes a fact sheet which has information about Miss Indian America IV, Sandra Mae Gover dated August 1956. Also included is a letter about Gover’s potential tour of Shrine hospitals across the country to visit crippled children and how to get the media involved. Gover’s authority on Indian Sign Language as well as her beauty and education are also cited as reasons to promote her charity work on television and radio.
  Also is a description of Mary Louise DeFender, a 23 year old Yanktonais Sioux Indian who won the title of Miss Indian America in 1954.
- Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Includes photographs of the following people:
  Joan Delphine Graves, Fairfax, Oklahoma, Osage- Pawnee, Sun-in- the Sky; Helen Sharon Miller, Serenade, Yakima Tribe, Wapato, Washington, 1952 Queen of the Yakima Tribe; Teresa Ambrose; Tommie Bachand Milwaukee, Wisconsion, Chippewa Tribe, Girl of the North; Susie Budd. Creek Indian,Tulsa, Oklahoma; Bailene de Sosa, Sioux; Wynena Rose Archambault.
- Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Includes the following photographs:
  Sandra Mae Gover of Pawnee, Miss Indian America IV; a Crow girl; a clipping from Spot News from Cleveland, Ohio dated November 20, 1955; Acey Blue Eagle- Pawnee; Mary Louise Defender poses for Ida Prokop Lee for Historic; N.D sculptured portrait Indian bust series (9th model); Rosa Mae Spencer and Nez Reid; Teresa Ambrose; Arapaho Dauer; Barbara Pappio, Kiowa Indian, Surgical nurse from Oklahoma City, 2nd place winner; Yakima group; Sandra Mae Gover, Pawnee, and Lula Real Rider, Pawnee; Group of Sioux; U.S. Judge Zahn “Flying Cloud” Northern Sioux; Sandra Mae Gover, Pawnee; Blackfoot dancers; Caroline Motanic of Pilot Rock, Oregon. August 1955; a photograph of Defender, McLaughlin, Archambault, Whilethum, de Sersa; Motanic Umatilla dancers.
- Informational sheets on the American Indian, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Includes entries on Wigwam and Flathead Indians in Montana, the Pueblo of Arizona, the Hopi Indians of New Mexico, the Seminole of Florida and the Indians of Peru and Panama. Each card features information on housing, the roles of men, women and children and various rituals.
- Newspaper Clippings, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Includes Chicago Daily Tribune article from September 3, 1956 featuring a photo of Sandra Stuart, Miss Chicago and Sandra Mae Gover, Miss Indian America, on a train to the Miss America pageant in Atlantic City.
- Photographs, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Includes a photo of Miss Indian America contestant at the Miss America pageant of 1955. Also includes the following: A photo of Williams, Ambrose, de Sersa and Motanic on the Miss America stage. A photo of Arlene Wesley, 1953 Queen, Mary Turley, Mary Louise Defender, Queen 1954, Kay Price, Wynema Rose Archambault as the 1st Miss Indian America greets the new Miss Indian America and her court. A photo of Kay Price.
- Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Contains the following photographs: Caroline Motanic, Umatilla; Jimmy Goes by the Door- Blackfeet dancers; Mary Geneva Whiteman- Crow; Darlene Desersa- Black Hills woman- Brule Sioux, Rapid City, South Dakota. Sponser: Rapid City Shrine Club; Mary Louis Defender, Red Earth Woman, Sioux, North Dakota; Mr. and Mrs. Ernest Charles James on their wedding day. The bride is Arlene Wesley, Miss Indian America I; Arlene Wesley, Miss Indian America I, Yakima Indian, Washington. (Seated on a horse in costume. The following information is written on the back of the photo in pencil. 20 years old, 5’ 1 1/2 “, 100 lbs, costume weight: 40 lbs).
- Photographs (contestant head shots and biographies), 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  The following photographs are included: Caroline Rosemary Motanic. Tsa-Loo. Umatilla Tribe. Pilot Rock, Oregon. Winner American Beauty Contest 1952. Princess of Chief Joseph Days.
  The following head shots and biographies are also included: Theresa Anne Ambrose, Yakima; Myrna May Williams, Cayuse; Darlene Desersa, Rosebud Sioux; Wynema Rose Archambault, Pawness- Sioux; Ramona LaVaun Mills, Sioux; Rosa Mae Margaret Spencer, Nez Perce; Sandra Ma Gover, Pawnee; Betty Jean Lunderman, Blackfeet; Roberta Jean Buck, Assiniboine; Jeannette Roselyn Weslye, Yakima; Barbara Louise Hudson, Osage; Hansa Fay Spang, Cheyenne.
  All biographies include the contestant’s age, tribe, height, weight, famous ancestors, hobbies and education.
  Other photographs: Mary Louise Defender turning over her title to Rita Ann McLaughlin; Miss Indian America III (Rita Ann McLaughlin) and her court which includes Mary Louise Defender, Miss Indian America II, and 1955 runners up Wyema Rose Archambault, Mary Geneva Whiteman and Sandra Mae Gover; a photo of the finalists; a photo of the wives of the chiefs; Mary Louise Defender, Miss Indian America II, 1954; Arlene Josephine Wesley, Miss Indian America I, 1953; a photo of two Miss Americas: Lee Ann Meriweather, Miss America 1955 of California, poses with Rita Ann McLaughlin, Miss Indian America 1955; an advertisement for the “Miss (Indian) America Contest, 1955” and photos of the pageant dated August 8, 1954.
- Correspondence of Dr. Herbert O. Brayer, 1949- 1957 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Most of the correspondence is to or from Herbert O. Brayer and range from 1949 to 1957. Also undated copies of the contestant’s biographies are included.
- Clippings, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Includes clippings of two different newspapers, the Phoenix Gazette and the Sheridan Press, which include articles about Delores Jean Short being crowned Miss Indian America in August 1957.
- Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  The following photographs are contained in this folder:
  Kay Price, 85 years old and Chris Chilli- grandmother of Sheep Springs, New Mexico. A photo of Teresa Ambrose, Umatilla; de Sersa, Sioux; Caroline Montanic, Umatilla; Sandra Mae Gover, Pawnee. A photo of Vivian Old Horn- Crow. Photo of Wynema Rose Archambault, Pawnee- Sioux; Mary Geneva Whiteman, Crow; Rose Mae Spencer, Nez Perce; Myrna Mae Williams and Teresa Ambrose. Photo of Eileen Bull over the Hill, Crow. Photo of Rosaline Bull over the Hill, Crow. Eileen Bull over the Hill, Crow. Mary Louise Defender, Miss Indian America, 1954-1955, Sioux; Rita Ann McLaughlin, Miss Indian America, 1955-1956, Sioux; Wynema Rose Archambault, Pawnee-Sioux; Mary Geneva Whiteman, Crow. Martin Cross and son Alfred, Outstanding Indian soldier, Sioux. Arapabo and new chief in a circle. Sandra Mae Gover. Joe Medicine, Crow. Chief Caleb Carter, “Otter Robe”, Nez Perce tribe. Blackfeet east of Glacier Park. Chief Iron Hail, Sioux, 98 years old and Dewey Bird and his wife. Steve White Hip, Harford White Hip, Chas Real Bird, Vincent Goes Ahead. Umatilla Indian Dancers from Washington doing a traditional fertility dance at All American Indian Days, Sheridan, Wyoming. Pawnee dancers. Jemez Indians (New Mexico) dancing the Pueblo Indian dance at All American Indian Days. Pawnee dancers from Oklahoma. Crow and Cheyenne girl dancers. Chief Little Crow, grandson of Minnesota War chieftain and Chief F.B. Zahn, Hunkpapa Sioux chief and Judge of the Supreme Court of the Dakota tribes. Jemez Eagle Dancer. Jemez Eagle Dancer. Photo of Luke Rock. “Mine Eyes Have Seen” Donald Deer Nose, Crow Tribe, General Chairman of the All American Indian department. Tom Yellowtail. Mollie Janis.
- Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  This folder contains the following photographs: Portraits of Rita McLaughlin; Wynema Archambault A photo ofJoyce Elaine Arrowchis, Fort Duchesne, Utah. Ute tribe. Indians of South America map and information, National Geographic, 1982. 2 negatives of tribes members in traditional dress next to teepee. A photo of Mary Louise Defender, Miss Indian America II, Fort Yates, North Dakota in Sioux dress. A Certificate of Support of All American Indian Days issued to Dr. Herbert O. Brayer and Mrs. Garnet Brayer. All American Indians Days is defined on the certificate as “a human relations project, in which Indian and White Citizens cooperate- to build better Interracial Understanding- to Perpetuate Indian Legend, Arts and Crafts- to contribute to Shriners Hospitals for Crippled Children and to promote the Preservation of our American Way of Life.”
- Entry forms, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Entry forms for the Miss (Indian) American III pageant 1955. Contains the following contestants’ forms: Caroline Rosemary Motanic, Theresa Ann Ambrose, Wyema Rose Archambault, Sandra Mae Gover, Rosa Mae Margaret Spencer, Rita Ann McLaughlin, Mary Geneva Whiteman, Darlene Desersa, Myrna May Williams.
- All American Indian Days, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  This folder includes a schedule of All American Indian Days August 6 and 7, 1955. Also includes official program, tickets to All American Indian Days and a general information brochure.
- Correspondence, 1954- 1955 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Correspondence of Herbert O. Brayer, L.T. Henderson and F.H. Sinclair July 28, 1954- August 24, 1955.
- Judges’ notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Includes judges’ notes on contestants. The judges made note of each contestant’s height, weight, tribe and age.
- Postcards and correspondence, 1948- 1957 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  This folder includes Little Red Sky, an informational pamphlet for children about a Native American boy named Little Red Sky who visits the dentist from 1948. Also included are blank postcards of Hopi Indians and the correspondence of Herbert O. Brayer, January- February 1957.
- Miss America pageant clippings and programs, 1954- 1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Contains Miss America programs from 1954- 1956. Also clippings which depict local pageant coverage in 1954 and 1955 in Atlantic city.
- All American Indian Days clippings and programs, 1954- 1957 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  This folder contains programs from All American Indian Days 1954- 1956 and a clipping about the event in the Sheridan Press.
- Tourism brochures, 1956- 1957 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Oklahoma, Tulsa and Wyoming tourist brochures.
- Herbert O. Brayer papers, 1945- 1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  This folder contains the folliwng: photos of Herbert O.Brayer, 1952; a letter to Dr. Ben M. Charrington, Director of the Social Science Foundation in 1945; undated poems; two copies of This Week in Chicago from February 195 and a program of Brayer’s memorial service in 1984.
- Judges' Papers, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Papers of the judges during the Miss Indian America pageant in 1955. This includes a note from Wynema Archambault stating that she cannot fulfill the appointments and duties of Miss Indian America and asking to be placed secondly. Also included is a pair of tickets to the event. Extensive notes on the contestants’ names, tribal name, tribes, height, weight, talent and age from the judges are also in this folder.
- The Sheridan Press clippings, 1955- 1957 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Clippings from August 3 1955- August 1, 1957 which includes coverage of All American Indian Days.
- Chicago Newspapers clippings, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Clippings covering Herbert Brayer’s involvement in the pageant and the contestants and their travels from the Chicago Sun Times and Chicago Tribune.
- Atlantic City Newspaper clippings, 1954- 1957 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Miss America Pageant coverage.
- Miscellaneous newspaper clippings, 1954- 1957 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  The following clippings are included: Denver Post, August 5, 1957; Salt Lake Tribune, August 16, 1956; Rocky Mountain News August 5, 1957; Rocky Mountain News August 15, 1955; The Billings Gazette August 15, 1955; The William Feather Magazine August 1955; The Best Western Travel Guide 1955 and Philadelphia Daily News September 8, 1954.
- Sheridan Press clippings, 1956- 1957 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  All American Indian Days coverage.
- Sandra Mae Gover photograph, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Undated photograph of Miss Indian America contestant, Sandra Mae Gover.
- Federated Indian Tribal Singers Record, undated (Box 5, Item 1)
  Record with “authentic American Indian songs”.
- Randy Steffan prints, undated (Box 5, Item 2)
  5 prints signed by Randy Steffen: teepee construction, men and horse competition, tribesmen singing and playing drums and spear throwing.
- Holiday Magazine article, 1956 (Box 5, Item 3)
  Article from Holiday Magazine entitled “The American Indian” by Jack Schaefer.